<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon on Phil. IV., 11, 12. For I have learned in whatsoever state I am in therewith to be content I know both how to be abased, and I know how to abound; every where, and in all things, I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5131A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230357</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895994</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895994</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153618</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93751)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153618)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2372:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon on Phil. IV., 11, 12. For I have learned in whatsoever state I am in therewith to be content I know both how to be abased, and I know how to abound; every where, and in all things, I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by Ralph Simpson, at the Harp in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Richard Stafford.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians IV, 11-12 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153618:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON
<q>
                  <bibl>Phil. IV. 11, 12.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For I have Learned in whatſoever State I am in therewith to be content. I know both how to be abaſed, and I know how to abound; Every where, and in all things, I am inſtructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer need.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>THeſe latter Words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> do cheifly and immediately relate to that two fold Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Life, Proſperity or Adverſity, Plenty or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, in the one of which all People are in, or in an even middle State between them both. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by Gods aſſiſtance (which I do humbly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly pray for, <hi>O ſend out thy Light and thy Truth, let them lead me.)</hi> I ſhall endeavour to treat of them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Limitation and Reſtriction; That we may know how to demean, behave and carry our ſelves, either in Proſperity or Adverſity, either in Plenty or under Poverty, or in that even middle State and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition between them both. So that, <hi>Every where, and in all things we may be inſtructed, both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer need.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153618:2"/>
            <p>When I have felt and experienced within my ſelf, ſome Covetings and Aſpirings above my preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, I have checked the ſame again with this thought and conſideration, That if I my ſelf were to be upon a level and an equality with the reſt of Mankind, I ſhould not then have ſo much, nor yet ſo good of the ſort of outward things, as I have had throughout all my paſt Life, and yet I have right unto. And I both know and have often reaſoned within my ſelf, That the ſame God who cauſed me to have been born of ſuch Parents, might have made me a Beggars Off-Spring, and have at firſt placed me in the Loweſt and Pooreſt State and Condition, that any of his reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are in throughout this Earth. This following Scripture hath run very much in my mind, <hi>When the moſt High divided to the Nations their Inheritance, when He ſeparated the Sons of</hi> Adam, <hi>He ſet the bounds of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple according to the Number of the Children of Iſrael,</hi> Deut. 32. 8. It is here ſaid, <hi>According to the Number of the Children of Iſrael:</hi> So He did at firſt things near by an Equality; and accordingly He doth now proportion it out both to this and to other Nations and Countreys. Allotting to each ſuch a Number of Inhabitants, as He knows it will conveniently feed and maintain. And after that, God had in his Infinite Knowledge and Wiſdom ſo <hi>divided to the Nations,</hi> and ſet forth the bounds of the People according to the Number of its ſeveral Inhabitants, Evil came preſently afterwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, with Covetouſneſs and Diſcontent, and the Sons of Violence and Tranſgreſſion Sprang up. Wickedneſs quickly Got head and the greater part of its ſide. And then ſome by Labour and Induſtry ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained what others through Negligence and Idleneſs parted withal, the World going on in the uſual way as it doth now. But the Great Landlord of all <hi>(Whoſe is the Earth and the fullneſs thereof)</hi> hath originally
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153618:2"/> given enough for all for the Fruits and Cattel (Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be his Goodneſs) are abundantly ſufficient to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all its Inhabitants: But He hath ſet Limits, Bounds, and Landmarks, that every one might know what was his own with a ſevere forbidding, and <hi>Curſe</hi> Annexed to him that <hi>Shall remove his Neighbours Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi> We may here uſe ſuch Boldneſs of Speech, God, who giveth the Beaſts their Food, and the young Ravens which cry, is, if we may ſo ſpeak, bound, (that is, it is a thing which belongs to him, and is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from him) to give neceſſary Food unto his Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Creatures; and accordingly He doth ſo ſtand obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Covenant; yea, and He doth perform the ſame: That is to ſay, To ſupply real Wants and not unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Luſts; to give what is abſolutely neceſſary or ſufficient, but not ſuperfluities, or needleſs things. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Fowls of the Air for they ſow not, neither do they reap, nor Gather into Barns; Yet your Heavenly Father feedeth them.</hi> Mat. 6. 26. We may as it were ſee with our Eyes his watchful and eſpecial Providence (or providing, for that is the proper ſignification of the Word Providence) over all his Living Creatures. <hi>The Eyes of all wait upon thee, and thou giveſt them their meat in due ſeaſon. Thou openeſt thine hand and ſatisfieſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of every Living thing.</hi> Pſal. 145. 15, 16. Who <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereto</hi> the Heaven with Clouds, who prepareth rain for the Earth, <hi>Who maketh Graſs to Grow upon the mountains.</hi> He <hi>giveth to the Beaſt his Food, and to the young Ravens which cry,</hi> Pſal. 147. 8, 9. Are ye not much better then they? Yea, much more Men and Women, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of the Creation of God, are under his Care and Proviſion.</p>
            <p>Every leaſt Part, Word and Syllable in Scripture is ſignificative, and when it is Written, <hi>I know that the Lord will maintain the Right of the Poor.</hi> Pſal. 140 12. We may hence aſſuredly Gather and Conclude, That
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153618:3"/> the Poor have as much <hi>Right</hi> unto neceſſary Food and Raiment, as any have to his Houſe, Lands, or Money. I will go on to add, and I will prove it: That they have more and greater <hi>Right</hi> unto that by this Law and true ſaying of God, then they have a right unto the other things, only by the Laws and Eſtabliſhment of Man. Now the firſt is of as much greater Force and Authority, as the Law of God is above the Law of Man, which is as much as God is greater then Man; which again, is as much as the vaſt fabrick of the World doth exceed in bulk, and dimenſion one ſingle duſt of the Ballance, or the leaſt Grain of Sand.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas it is Written, <hi>When the Poor and Needy ſeek water and there is none, and their Tongue fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for Thirſt, I the Lord will hear them, I the God of</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob <hi>will not forſake them.</hi> Iſa. 41. 17. How is this ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled and found true? For I my ſelf, have ſeen a Poor and Needy Creature look with much Earneſtneſs and Anguiſh for a meal of Victuals, when He hath been hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bitten, and for all that, He hath been at length forced to go away without it: Nevertheleſs this Promiſe of God ſtands firm and ſure to ſuch as to futurity, and in the time of the reſtitution of all things, it will be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally made Good. But here again it may be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, What is this the near, if one ſhall be famiſhed in the mean while, as I have heard that in an hard Winter, or in a Dearth or ſcarcity of Victuals, ſome have dyed for want of neceſſaries. The ſin whereof will be required of that reſpective Place and Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the Inhabitants thereof could have poſſibly prevented and avoided it. Yet ſtill there is a great deal in this Promiſe of God, for <hi>He that turneth Man to Deſtruction, will ſay, Return ye Children of Men,</hi> Pſal. 90. 3. He will raiſe up and reſtore that ſame Life which they loſt, and will ſo order the matter that it ſhall never be loſt again, by changing it into
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153618:3"/> 
               <hi>Life for evermore.</hi> But herein eſpecially, is that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe fulfilled at this preſent Time, <hi>When the Poor and Needy ſeek water and there is none, and their Tongue faileth for Thirſt, I the Lord will hear them, I the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>will not forſake them;</hi> That is, what is of God and appears forth in any of his Saints, Servants and Creatures; This Godlike Nature and Diſpoſition, doth actually reach forth Bread and Water to them that need it. So much as is of God in any Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, will hear the Poor and Needy, ſo as to give what they ask and to grant their Requeſts, and will not <hi>forſake them:</hi> for it is a certain Rule, that where any one is hard hearted, or cloſe fiſted towards the Poor and Needy, there is little of God, or Goodneſs in that Man or Woman. As again, on the other hand, where is Compaſſion or bounty towards them according to our ſeveral Ability, It is not ſo much we which do that Good deed, but God and Chriſt that dwelleth in us. It is the Spirit of him doth Act in and through us, who hath promiſed and doth perform it, <hi>When the Poor and Needy ſeek Water, and there is none, and their Tongue faileth for Thirſt, I the Lord will hear them, I the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>will not forſake them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having Diſcourſed theſe Truths, in the General and by way of Introduction to the following matter, (which ſame Truths, are neceſſary and uſeful to be made known) Let us come ſomewhat nearer to our intended Subject in hand.</p>
            <p>It hath been ſaid, That Nature is content with a little, but certain it is, that Grace is content with leſs. We are expreſly told, that <hi>Godlineſs with contentment is great Gain,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 6. Which exactly Anſwers to what hath been aforeſaid, how that <hi>Paul</hi> had ſo <hi>Learned in whatſoever ſtate he was in therewith to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> That what would be really and indeed want un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others, was no want unto him. Even ſo it is here
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153618:4"/> again; for ſpeaking in the foregoing Verſe, of <hi>Men of corrupt Minds and Deſtitute of the Truth, ſuppoſing that gain is Godlineſs;</hi> That is, they imagine that to get Gain, that is ſerving God and Anſwering the ends of their Creation; and minding their buſineſs, that is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. (We have many that talk after the very ſame manner in theſe our days) In Anſwer to whom comes in this Precious Truth, <hi>Godlineſs with contentment is great Gain.</hi> That is, Godlineſs with contentment is Equivalent and doth contain in it, and is altogether as Good as real Gain; for it doth all one, and as much (I ſay, more) help and contribute to the well Being and Happineſs of Man as the other doth. But this is a myſtery to Wordlings, and an Art which cannot be by them underſtood and apprehended, <hi>How that a little that a righteous man hath, is better then the riches of many Wicked,</hi> Pſal. 37. 16. <hi>Better is a little with Righteouſneſs, then Great Revenues without right,</hi> How that the <hi>having neither Poverty nor Riches,</hi> but being <hi>fed with Food con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for us,</hi> when this is joyned with the knowledge and fear of the Lord, with the Practice of Univerſal Chriſtianity, ſhall make Men and Women to live more ſweetly and comfortably, then ten times the quantity and abundance without it; All this is Parable and Myſtery (tho the thing is true, and experienced by his Saints and Servants) and as a ſtrange thing to the People of the World; Beſides that aſſured Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Tendency which it hath unto Eternal ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>Thou haſt put gladneſs into my Heart, more then in the time that their Corn and their Wine increaſed,</hi> Pſal. 4. 7. But how common is it with the People of the World in their Contracts and ſuch like, to judge and eſteem of each Perſon according to what Money or Lands they have, more then according to what and Perſon is. For alas! In this thing they are Ignorant, that Grace and Goodneſs, Knowledge and Wiſdom in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153618:4"/> any Man or Woman, will lay in a better and more ſure Foundation for a comfortable contented and happy Life, even in this World, then Thouſands of Gold and Silver; Beſides, that all this is the only means to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the being ſaved and bleſſed in the World to come, into which we are all juſt entring.</p>
            <p>But obſerve further, with what kind of unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reaſoning the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth back and confirm the aforementioned Truth, <hi>Godlineſs with Contentment is great Gain.</hi> Thereupon He immediately adds and ſubjoyns, <hi>For we brought nothing into this World, and it is certain we can carry nothing out.</hi> Then He takes up again the ſame Exhortation, and having aforeſhewed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and alſo the reaſon thereof, <hi>And having Food and Raiment, let us therewith be content,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>This State of having juſt Food and Raiment is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Plenty nor yet Poverty, but that even middle State between them both. And if we can be content therewith, as alſo be content with Plenty, and what is yet harder, Be content under Poverty, <hi>Why then eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, and in all things we are inſtructed, both to be full and to be hungry, to abound and ſuffer need.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no ſuch great matter in being content amidſt Plenty and Proſperity may ſome imagine, but even in them the Leſſon of Contentment is to be Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Practiſed; for there is a tireſomneſs and unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactoryneſs even in Plenty and Proſperity it ſelf; for the Spirit may be obſerved to be even then reſtleſs and troubled. Which doth partly ariſe from the inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency in the thing it ſelf, to give real contentment and ſatisfaction to the Soul and Heart of Man. For Plenty and Proſperity do cheifly relate to outward things, and theſe do pertain only to the Body. So that it is no more to be wondred, that the Soul ſhould ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unſatisfied even whilſt the Body hath them, then that the Body ſhould ſuffer hunger, even whilſt the Soul
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153618:5"/> is fed with her proper Food, the Words of Knowledge and Wiſdom. As alſo a diſcontent doth ariſe even amidſt Plenty and Proſperity, when People do not know fully and throughly the Nature of things, and then they do not ſubordinate things rightly according to their ſeveral Ends and Objects; Or, they do not ſuffer the ſtream of their affections to fix on thoſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which are moſt worthy, and that is God and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality. They imagine and place too much good in Temporal and Viſible things; and again they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine and place too little or leſs Good, and eſteem in Eternal, Inviſible and Spiritual things then really there is in them: Or rather, they do croſs, and act contrary to that Rule and Direction of the Apoſtle, <hi>Set your Affection on things above, and not on things on the Earth,</hi> Coloſ. 1. 3. For it is too evident and certain, That moſt People (even among thoſe who ſeem to be Religious alſo) do ſet their Affection, or as it is in the marginal reading, their mind on things on the Earth and not on things above. And thence it comes to paſs, that tho' they have their full and plenty of the things of this Earth, yet the <hi>Creature being made Subject to Vanity,</hi> Rom. 8. 20. And there being an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency or Inability in it, to give real Peace and Reſt, or Contentment to the Soul of Man, thereupon (that is from this <hi>Vanity)</hi> doth ariſe <hi>Vexation of Spirit.</hi> So that it is too true (for the ſame is ſeen and experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, That ſeveral People have fullneſs and abundance and yet they have not Contentment: The want where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of makes them to go out again, and betake themſelves to further Coveteouſneſs and its appendant of injuſtice and wrong, to the <hi>Pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon,</hi> and to thoſe ſeveral kinds of Mad and Frantick Actions which are done throughout this Earth. <hi>Thou art wearied in the Greatneſs of thy way, yet ſaidſt thou not there is no Hope,</hi> Iſa. 57. 10. And ſo they are tired and wearied
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153618:5"/> in looking out and ſeeking after ſatisfaction; yet they will go on ſtill to expect the ſame and not ſit down perſwaded, that there is no ſatisfaction to be had from the things of this World. And then here is their fault Now and Vexation, and will be their Puniſhment and Miſery hereafter, that for all it is ſo, Nevertheleſs, they will not turn the current and ſtream of their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from the things on Earth, and lift up their mind and ſet their affection on things above: For if they once did that, then all would go right again and as it ſhould be; for they ſhould be ſought after and Minded and Loved in the firſt Place, and all other things ſhould be brought in Subordination, ſubſervien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and tendency to them.</p>
            <p>Now the Grace and Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt (which the People of the World have not, or at leaſt do not act by) doth all this, and ſupply what is wanting and defective in them. For as that doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and acquaint us of <hi>things preſent, and things to come,</hi> of what things pertain to the Body and what pertain to the Soul; what doth belong to the life that now is, which is as a Vapour and continueth not, and what relates unto future and endleſs Life. As hereby we know the Order, Connexion and Subordination of things one to another, and as we give to each thing its proportion and weight, and no more, and ſo labour and ſeek after it accordingly, thus the <hi>Grace of God which bringeth Salvation;</hi> Thus the Grace and Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt bringeth Contentment; <hi>And it hath appeared unto all Men.</hi> For God hath ſhewed it unto them, or it is within them, <hi>Teaching them,</hi> or in the Phraſe of our Text, <hi>Every where, and in all things, inſtructing them both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer need.</hi> This way only, may any one learn to be content amidſt Plenty and Proſperity.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153618:6"/>
            <p>But as ſaith the Proverb, <hi>Of all ſorrows, a fat ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is beſt:</hi> So there ſeems to be no ſuch great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to learn to be content when in the Prophets Phraſe, <hi>Their Portion is Fat and their Meat Plenteous,</hi> Hab. 1. 16. <hi>Their Eyes ſtand out with Fatneſs, they have more then heart could wiſh,</hi> Pſal. 73. 7. But indeed there is greater difficulty to be content under Adverſity and Poverty. Here again, all things are equally poſſible to an Almighty Power; for the ſame Grace and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jeſus Chriſt which doth <hi>inſtruct how to be full,</hi> will alſo <hi>inſtruct how to be hungry, and how to ſuffer need,</hi> all one as <hi>how to abound.</hi> I will aſſure ye, hunger and need are ſenſible things; for altho' thoſe that are full, can ſpeak lightly and diſdainfully thereof, yet they are indeed afflicting and ſore Evils. Here again conceive or feel it in its very worſt, yet the Grace and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks a Word of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and Contentment, as it ſaith on this wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let not your heart be troubled, ye believe in God, believe alſo in me.</hi> So O Man or Woman, be not troubled if thou art in want here, for that will be ended; but have together with it <hi>Poverty of Spirit,</hi> (which ſhuts out all Murmuring and Aſpiring Thoughts) and then <hi>yours is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 5. 3. Which is Everlaſting, and will have no End. <hi>And Jeſus lifted up his Eyes on his Diſciples and ſaid, Bleſſed be ye Poor for yours is the Kingdom of God. Bleſſed are ye that hunger now, for ye ſhall be filled. Bleſſed are ye that weep now, for ye ſhall laugh,</hi> Luk. 6. 20, 21. Why ſhould People be cumbred and make ſuch a ſtir about the things of this Life; for the Rejoycing or Vexation, as to their abundance or want, expires with the moment before us. Every Revolution of the Sun, the Night comes and ſhuts up all. Thoſe who did Cry or Laugh, are in deep ſilence. The Laborious or Idle Perſons are at reſt. And here it is found true, the ſleep of a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153618:6"/> Man is ſweet, but the lazineſs, fullneſs, or guilt of others makes that it doth not become ſo unto them. The fine Cloaths are laid aſide, and ſo is the vile Raiment The mouth is ſtill, or ſhut with Sleep that fed upon Dainties, or common fare. Many are apt to ſtomach it, and have Indignation that they are forced to feed upon courſe Food. But is not the fleſh that feeds upon it, groſs and filthy alſo? And doth it not become more filthy when it is caſt our into the drought and goes forth in Excrements. Every thing that People Eat or Drink, is more fine and clean in its kind, then the Belly, or thoſe uncomely parts of us, which receives it in and vents it. Be not offended, for even in the Scriptures we meet with theſe very ſame, or ſuch kind of Expreſſions; as indeed, ſometimes they are neceſſary to be uſed in bringing out the very Truth. And ſo do People grudge at and are aſhamed of their <hi>Vile Raiment,</hi> Jam. 2. 2. I would only ask ſuch as think ſo, Is it not a <hi>Vile Body,</hi> Phil. 3. 21. That is to be arrayed therewith? The Goodneſs, or Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Man doth not conſiſt in theſe things, which are meerly extrinſical unto him. And as our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt did ſay, <hi>ſufficient unto the day is the evil thereof.</hi> So here it may be conceived, as the ſame is known and experienced, that the outward good or evil of each day is determined and finiſhed with the day, which goeth and paſſeth away, and it is as a Dream when one awaketh, For what much greater difference is there betwen yeſterday's Actions and Doings, and laſt nights Dream. As one day and night is to the time of our Sojourning here, ſo is the whole as to Eternity and future Life. The things which we have already done, would not profit, unleſs we did build on further and finiſh them: So it will be of all labour done as to the things here, which will have an end, and ſignifie nothing; but yet the good
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153618:7"/> or evil of each thing will come into judgment; <hi>For God will bring every ſecret thing into judgment, with every work, whether it be good or bad,</hi> Eccleſ. 12. 14. So that each deed done in the Body (though it is over and paſt) will tend to our benefit or loſs at that day.</p>
            <p>Now as it is written, <hi>This ſpake he ſignifying by what death he ſhould glorifie God,</hi> Joh. 21. 19. So this is the thing to be attended unto, and endeavoured after, by what life we ſhall glorifie God. So that if we can and alſo do glorifie God in our Adverſity and Poverty, it will be better unto us than to have had Plenty and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And as it is elſewhere written, <hi>Abraham was ſtrong in Faith, giving glory unto God,</hi> Rom. 4. 20 ſo it is here; he that is content under Adverſity and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, the ſame Perſon doth <hi>give glory unto God.</hi> How ſo? After the ſame manner as <hi>Abraham</hi> did; <hi>for he ſtaggered not at the promiſe of God through unbelief, and is fully perſwaded, that what God hath promiſed he was able alſo to perform;</hi> how that he will <hi>ſave the poor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted People,</hi> and that he will give unto his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures yet better things in the future ſtate, which the contented Chriſtian doth firmly believe, and patiently wait for. For though he might remedy or get out of his preſent adverſe and poor Condition by ſinful or evil means, yet he will not conſent unto, nor do them. Thus while he is under thoſe outward evils and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, he <hi>doth not charge God fooliſhly,</hi> nor yet ſuffer his heart to fret againſt him, nor yet will he ſin to be eaſed or delivered out of them. In all this he doth glorifie, or give glory unto God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Love not the World, neit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er the things that are in the World,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 15. One reaſon of this is added, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. which though it is expreſſed in ſhort, is of mighty force and cogency; <hi>and the World paſſeth away and the luſt thereof.</hi> This is neceſſary to perſwade and exhort unto, and for People to practiſe and obſerve,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153618:7"/> in order to Contentment; for almoſt all diſcontent doth ariſe from too much love of and hankering after the things of this World, and imagining more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction therein than really there is; and thence it is that People are ſo vexed and upon the fret to miſs of or be diſappointed of them. But if there is no love placed thereon, according as this Divine Command runs, then if we have the things of this World, we may be thankful and moderate in the uſe of them, and alſo be ſo much the more patient in Spirit if we have them not. Nothing is ſo apt to make us indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and unconcerned as to them, as a thorow know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſideration of the Tranſitorineſs and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of all the things of this World. <hi>They all paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and they are vain.</hi> Saith God in <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 8. 13. <hi>The things that I have given them ſhall paſs away from them.</hi> Let the Reader call to mind all the enjoyments that he ever had in all his paſt Life, and what doth remain out of them at this preſent moment? He is deſired not to make the reflection in Sickneſs, or on a Death-bed, but even now, in the day of Health, and whilſt he hath and enjoys them. Are they not the very ſame as if they were never perceived or had? Thou canſt think upon ſuch a day that was paſt in joviality and merriment, and another which went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in vexation and dulneſs; compare them both now together, and what advantage hath one over the other? There is no difference of happineſs or miſery as to the paſt.</p>
            <p>There is ſuch a do and ſtir made in the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Proſperity and Adverſity; how wonderfully careful, diligent and ſolicitous are People to have the firſt, and how wonderfully afraid are they, and how do they ſeek to avoid the other? And yet for all, take the Galley-Slave who hath for ſo many days or years toiled at the Oar, or the vagrant Beggar, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153618:8"/> who hath led the moſt miferable, laborious, and tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome life. And on the other ſide, take the World's moſt happy Minion, who hath had all things at will, and in the greateſt plenty; who hath paſt all his whole foregoing time in all health, mirth and jollity, and compare both theſe together; and as to all the paſt time of their reſpective Lives there is no odds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them both. It doth ſeem and appear ſo now, even whilſt we are in the midſt of one or the other; and much more will it ſeem and appear ſo, when we are tranſlated from Time to Eternity, from Earth to Heaven, <hi>and the former ſhall not be remembred, nor come into mind,</hi> Iſa. 65. 17. All the whole buſineſs, employment and ſmall variety of this preſent Life will be as a Dream when one awaketh, or as the Dream of a Night Viſion. And yet notwithſtanding all this Vanity, Tranſitorineſs, and paſſing away of things, yet according to the Good or Evil, Duty or Sin we have done and committed in this vain and tranſitory Life, it will proportionably tend to our advantage, or loſs, our reward or puniſhment for all Eternity. For God hath ſo ordained it, and he will accordingly do and recompence unto Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the reaſonable Inhabitants of this Earth. So that the right conſequence is, Art thou called in a proſperous and plentiful Condition of Life? Do all the good that ever thou canſt, and abſtain from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evil. <hi>Stand in awe and ſin not,</hi> and leave no Duty whatſoever undone. Thou art to do the very ſame alſo if thou art placed in a poor and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Condition; or if thou art in an even and mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſtate between them both, there <hi>Truſt in the Lord, and do good, ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the Land, and verily thou ſhalt be fed. Delight thy ſelf alſo in the Lord, and he ſhall give thee the deſires of thine heart,</hi> Pſal. 37. 3, 4.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:153618:8"/>
            <p>And what is the Deſires of thine heart? If thou art a Worldling, or Senſualiſt, then it is for plenty <hi>of Corn and Wine,</hi> for a good Eſtate, and for a great deal of Mony; for Health, and long Life, and ſuch like. I profeſs ſolemnly and ſeriouſly this is not the deſires of mine heart, for I would not be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and put off, if God Almighty ſhould ſay to me, thou ſhalt have the deſires of thine heart; or if the Lord ſhould appear to me in a Dream by Night, as he did to <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3. 5. (ſee it,) and ſay <hi>Ask what I ſhall give thee.</hi> I do here make known what in this caſe I would ask of God, Peace here, and Salvation hereafter; Contentment here, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that Reſt which remaineth for the People of God; Grace here, and Glory hereafter. <hi>Give there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy Servant an underſtanding heart, that I may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern between good and bad,</hi> ver. 9. Give me pardon and forgiveneſs of all my paſt Sins, in as full, free and ample manner as God hath any where promiſed in his word; and give to me grace, ſtrength and power to abſtain from Sin for the time to come, and that I may finiſh the Work which he hath ſent me on Earth for to do; and that I may perform all the mean and preparatory Acts which are neceſſary, that my Soul may be committed into the hands of God, and received up into Heaven, after it ſhall be diſlodged from this Body, or Tenement of Clay, wherein now for a very little time longer it doth inhabit and reſide. Theſe are the deſires of mine heart; and I do again truly declare, that I have not the leaſt deſire or coveting whatever, but what comes within or in ſubordination under theſe firſt and great deſires.</p>
            <p>If I have any further deſires after more Money or Eſtate than now I have, it is, not that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it upon my Luſts, <hi>James</hi> 4. 3. or upon my Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153618:9"/> (according to the Marginal reading there) or the pride of Life, but that I may hononr the Lord with my ſubſtance, and conſecrate my gain unto the Lord, and my ſubſtance unto the Lord of the whole Earth, <hi>Micah</hi> 4. 13. for then I would be ready to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute the ſame towards the outward charge and labour, for the publiſhing and propagation of his Eternal Truth. I would to God there was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame and alike mind in the Rich and ſubſtantial People: <hi>That they alſo would be Rich in good Works, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 18. and contribute towards it; for the Work of the Lord is common, and ſhould be the joynt endeavour of all his Servants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord hear thee in the day of trouble, the name of the God of Jacob defend thee, Grant thee according to thine own heart, and fulfill all thy Counſel,</hi> Pſal. 20. 1, 4. But if the Lord grant me according to mine own heart, and fulfill all my Counſell, then, as it is elſewhere written, <hi>the Lord hath d ne great things for us, whereof we are glad,</hi> Pſal. 126, 3. So the Lord would do great things for me; he would do even my all that I am capable of; that is, to ſerve him here according to his will, ſo that I may be accepted of him at the laſt, and obtain and be inveſted with Eternal Salvation.</p>
            <p>The ſame Lord who Created the Soul, Created thoſe <hi>Deſires</hi> alſo that are in the ſame Soul; and it may be obſerved that theſe Deſires are in relation and tendency unto, and they reach after ſomewhat which again is not vain; for the ſame God who firſt implanted in a deſire towards it, will after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards give the thing it ſelf. And this Deſire puts us upon uſing the Means, Labour, Endeavour, and ſeeking after it. Now the Complex and whole of the Deſire of Man is after theſe things (which are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153618:9"/> alſo connected together) Life, Happineſs, and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As the hungry craves after Food, the covetous Riches, the ambitious Honour, and every one Reſt and Satisfaction; and they will uſe alſo the common means in their own Power towards the having them. So likewiſe there is a deſire ingrafted into Man, after thoſe things which God hath promiſed. And it is but reaſonable he ſhould do ſo much towards obtaining them, as the Men of the World do for the things of this World; for otherwiſe he will come ſhort of them. And thoſe pertaining to the Kingdom of God, are ſet forth by the very ſame things, in a greater degree then what is ſo earneſtly followed after here. We ſhould do well to give heed, and attend unto the working of thoſe deſires within us, <hi>which way they make,</hi> and after what they do point and reach forth. If thoſe deſires be after Temporal and worldly Things; Here the beſt way is by contracting and leſſening of them; for a Man may ſooner draw off thoſe boundleſs and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſires, then he can fulfil them. He may be more quickly contented then great; and he will find it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to have been innocent, then to have been Rich. But if theſe Deſires do riſe up after Heavenly, Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and Eternal Things, there let God <hi>enlarge thy Heart,</hi> and in his Name deſire as much as ever thou wilt. The more thou deſireſt, if thou doſt accordingly labour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it with diligence, and earneſtneſs, the better it will be for thee, and the more thou wilt receive; for here the ſure word of promiſe is, <hi>Open thy Mouth wide, and I will fill it,</hi> Pſal. 81. 10. the wider it is opened, the more it will receive. And nothing is a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Truth (though we muſt apprehend and lay hold upon it by Faith, becauſe it will not be all fulfilled in this Life, and on this Earth) then that God will at length ſatisfie thoſe Deſires he hath put into us. <hi>He will fulfil the deſire of them that fear him.</hi> Pſal. 145. 19.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153618:10"/> This is expreſſed in the future tenſe, and in <hi>ver.</hi> 16. it is ſaid, <hi>He ſatisfieth the deſire of every living thing.</hi> That is ſpoken in the preſent tenſe, becauſe that belongs to the living and unreaſonable Creatures; for we may perceive evidently, that Beaſts, Birds, and Fiſhes, are contented and ſatisfied with the things before them; whereas Man is not. It is the ſame Creator of all: But hereby is ſhewn forth, that God will do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more for Man in the future ſtate of things, which he will not do for them. And hereunto is another Promiſe, <hi>The Lord will perfect that which concerneth me.</hi> Pſal. 138. 8. And we are to wait his good and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Time.</p>
            <p>Here this great Expectation from the laſt end and diſtribution of things, ſhould quiet and ſilence our Spirits every time they begin to riſe and be troubled. Who is much concerned for the pleaſantneſs or dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of a Dream, after that it is over and paſt? For there is no odds, and it is all near the ſame as to the good or evil nature thereof. All this may be learnt and underſtood as a Man.</p>
            <p>But then the Grace and Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt doth ſet before us ſuch very great, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, and enduring things, that the preſent is or ought to be no more minded in compariſon to them, then one who is in purſuit and likelihood to obtain ten thouſand Pounds, doth value or regard the loſs of a Pin, or of a Farthing. However unconcern'd he ſtands to it now, yet the reaſonable Creature can never be content to miſs of Happineſs and Salvation; and ſo he will manifeſt and make it appear when this Happineſs and Salvation comes to be preſent and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt before him; for therefore it is, that People do ſo little regard it, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeems future, and to be at a diſtance; and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this diſadvantage againſt all our Preaching, concerning which they imagine, <hi>He propheſieth of Times
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153618:10"/> afar off,</hi> Ezeck. 12. 27. Whereas all this great matter which is cryed up ſo much to be at a diſtance, and to be afar off, is no futher off then the death of each Man or Woman; which for ought we know, may be this Night, to Morrow, within a Week, or a Month, or a Year, as to the healthieſt, youngeſt, and luſtieſt of us all; which will moſt certainly come upon every one of us, one time or another. And then if there be amongſt ye, any prophane Perſon as <hi>Eſau,</hi> who for one morſel of Meat, ſold his Birth-right; who, for the Pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon, for the Reward of Iniquity, or the Gains of Unrighteouſneſs, hath forfeited his or her ſhare in that <hi>Bleſſing which the Lord hath commanded, even Life for evermore.</hi> Even theſe very ſame Perſons either when they come to lie in the point or extremity of Death, or more certainly, (becauſe many may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtupid or ignorant, or unbelieving even then) afterward that their Souls are gone forth into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible World, they would fain inherit the Bleſſing; and then <hi>they will ſeek for it carefully with Tears,</hi> though it will be to no purpoſe, for <hi>they will find no place for Repentance,</hi> becauſe here he <hi>gave them a ſpace for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and they repented not.</hi> Then (if ſuch a thing were poſſible, and might be admitted of, which yet is not) even thoſe very ſame Perſons would <hi>give thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Rams, and ten thouſand Rivers of Oyl, their firſt born, for their Tranſgreſſion, and the fruit of their Body for the ſin of their Soul;</hi> who now will not make Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution for one farthing of ill gotten Goods; nor yet hardly give a thouſand farthings in Alms giving, or towards good Works; or who will not now give up a Luſt, or a ſinful profit at all the commandments and Requirings of God. If any ſuch profane, careleſs, and indifferent Souls ſhould hear or read theſe lines, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I have told you before, I do hereby warn and make known unto ſuch before hand, that their Thoughts
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153618:11"/> and Apprehenſions will be thus mightily altered and changed, as to what they ſtand ſo unconcerned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected now; for as on the one hand it will be the beſt contentment, and greateſt ſatisfaction <hi>(I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs,</hi> Pſal. 17. 12.) to be poſſeſſed of, and make ſure of Heaven: So again, there will be no diſcontent ſo bad as that, to miſs and come ſhort thereof. This will be the <hi>gnawing of the Worm which ſhall never die.</hi> Of this kind will be that <hi>Indignation and Wrath, Tribulation and Anguiſh, which ſhall be upon every Soul of Man that doth evil,</hi> Rom. 2. 8, 9. <hi>There ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth, when ye ſhall ſee</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>in the Kingdom of God, and ye your ſelves thruſt out.</hi> Though as to theſe little, vain, and fugitive things, we may know and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and alſo bear with how to be full, or how to be hungry: But as to that <hi>fulneſs,</hi> or <hi>Hunger</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 21. 25. <hi>Bleſſed are ye that hunger now, for ye ſhall be filled. Wo unto you that are full, for ye ſhall hunger.</hi> Here it is Impoſſible even for the Tongue of Men and Angels to inſtruct the Creatures, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Souls to be contented and bear there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. The reaſonable Creature can never be content to loſe Heaven, and fall into Hell, becauſe of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding greatneſs of the loſs, that compleat and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Miſery this would be to be involved in, as alſo from the very long duration, and irreverſibleneſs thereof. If God comes to contend for ever in the Puniſhment and Miſery of his Creatures, and to be always wroth, then the Spirit ſhould fail before me, and the Souls which I have made.</p>
            <p>But on the other better hand, if one is a Child of God, and an Heir of the Kingdom of Heaven, then he can very well be contented under all the Evils and Hardſhips of this preſent World. All one as an Heir of a good Eſtate doth rub through ſome little and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153618:11"/> Inconveniencies in the mean while, out of Proſpect and Expectation of that. Beſides the Faith of Great and unſeen things which are Eternal, a through Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the littleneſs of all preſent and temporal things will ſoon make us content as to the having or not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them; or rather work us into that bleſſed Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Diſpoſition of <hi>Paul, As having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi> His Mind was ſo qualified with Grace, and transformed into the Divine Nature, that it was the ſame as if he poſſeſſed all things.</p>
            <p>As to the littleneſs of all preſent things, conſider within your ſelves, <hi>What is your Life? It is as a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour that appeareth for a very little time, and then vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away. Remember how ſhort my time is, Wherefore haſt thou made all Men in vain?</hi> Their Mirth or Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are as the flyings up and down of a Swallow, during its appointed time. Their heavineſs or Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeems all one as the mourning of a Dove, which alſo is ended. Whatever delights or afflicts, ſoon paſſeth away, and we are gone. As to our outward ſenſible good or evil, though we would fain have the one, and avoid the other; yet there is not much more in it, then the ticklings of a Feather, or to prevent the ſcratchings of a Pin. Our goings up and down each day, appear as the moving of a Shaddow, which is loſt in darkneſs. And ſo we might run through or over all the ſeveral things of this preſent Life, they are all little, fugitive, and vain.</p>
            <p>As on the one hand, this true conſideration is a mighty word of Comfort and Contentment to the Children of Faith, the Heirs of Life and Immortality; ſo on the other, the more knowing People of this World turn it into a matter of Scepticiſm; as alſo the more brutiſh, ignorant and ungodly ſort of People, do hereby harden and confirm themſelves in their old wonted manner of Life of Brutiſhneſs, Ignorance, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153618:12"/> Ungodlineſs; and they will not eaſily be brought off from it; for like as there are in the laſt days, <hi>Scoffers walking after their own ungodly Luſts, and ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his coming? For ſince the Fathers fell aſleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the Creation.</hi> So they imagine and reaſon within themſelves, What need of any words of Comfort or Contentment at all, ſeeing that all things here are ſo little, fugitive and vain? All things come alike to all. <hi>There is one Event to the Righteous and to the Wicked; to the good, to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth, and to him that ſacrificeth not; as is the Good, ſo is the Sinner. And he that ſweareth, as he that feareth an Oath.</hi> The World paſſeth away, and goes on in its courſe; and we will make a ſhift to rub through it as well as other People, and there is an end. Here hath been delivered a Diſcourſe concerning Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for all that, and all the words in the World concerning it, we do perceive that thoſe People live altogether as contented for the Life, who do not hear them, as thoſe who do hear them: As is the knowing Man, ſo is the ignorant Perſon; it ſeems to come all to one.</p>
            <p>By this Objection Satan works in the Minds of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny People, eſpecially of the common and poorer ſort; and hereby he ſerves the great Ends of his Kingdom of Darkneſs, in beating People off from God and good things. But to anſwer them in their own familiar way of ſpeaking, <hi>All is well that ends well.</hi> It is the ſame old thredbare Imagination of the People of former Generations, which is come down amongſt us alſo, and dwells in the Hearts of many People of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Generation. <hi>Ye have ſaid it is vain to ſerve God; and what profit is it that we have kept his Ordinances, and that we have walked mournfully before the Lord of Hoſts. Then they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153618:12"/> and the Lord hearkened and heard it, and a Book of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance was written before him for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his Name. And they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, in the day when I make up my Jewels; and I will ſpare them as a Man ſpareth his own Son that ſerveth him. Then ſhall ye return, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern between the Righteous and the Wicked; between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not.</hi> Mal. 3. 14, 16, 17, 18. So we refer our Objectors and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, thoſe ignorant and ungodly Perſons, that think thus in their Minds, over unto the day of Death, and of Judgment, when they ſhall ſee that twofold Diſtribution of things, that is to be made in the after State. True indeed, the End and Event is to prove all things. But whoſo ſuſpends his Faith until then, his Condition will be without Remedy. <hi>Then ſhall they return,</hi> that is, to the proper Underſtanding of Men, and diſcern, what before they might have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; for it was declared and told unto them over and over, that there ſhould be a diverſity made of Happineſs to the one, and Miſery to the other, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Righteous and the Wicked, between him that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth God, and him that ſerveth him not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to that great doubt and ſurmiſe which is in the Thoughts of the Heart of almoſt every one, How that all things happen alike to all, and that there is one and the ſame Event to Godly or Ungodly, Righteous or Wicked, I have in a printed Sermon on <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 2. opened and explained that Myſtery, wherein I have ſhewed and aſſigned the very Reaſon thereof, Why God ordained it ſo to be, Namely, That it is to <hi>prove</hi> the Children of Men, <hi>To know what is in their Heart, whether they will keep his Commandments or no.</hi> Indeed, if People were not ſtill puzzled and perplexed; if they did not <hi>alway err in their Heart,</hi> Heb. 3. 10. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at his Soul is <hi>grieved,</hi> they would never imagine and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153618:13"/> talk after that manner, That it was the ſame thing, whether they heard or received into their Knowledge, words of Comfort or Contentment, or not; for they may, yea and they do think and ſay the ſame, as to the other words of Grace and Salvation al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o. I would ask ſuch vain Imaginers, and fooliſh Reaſoners, Is it the ſame thing as to natural <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ife, Whether they do eat and drink, or they do not? No, here they will ſay, It is not; for except we eat and drink, we muſt famiſh and dye. Even ſo it is here in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, though they can be hardly made to apprehend this; <hi>for the natural Man diſcerneth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs unto him; neither can he know them, bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> As <hi>Simeon waited for the Conſolation of Iſrael,</hi> ſo the Soul cannot be comforted without the words of Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. The Soul cannot poſſibly be ſaved and happy, without the words of Salvation and Happineſs. As the Body would die for want of Suſtenance, ſo the Soul may be indeed held in ſuſpence a little longer time, even all the days it is in the Body; whereas that cannot be much longer without Food then four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days: So without the words of Knowledge and Salvation, the Soul would die Eternally, and fall down into Miſery. <hi>Send Men to</hi> Joppa, <hi>and call for</hi> Simon, <hi>whoſe Surname is</hi> Peter, <hi>who ſhall tell thee words, whereby thou and thy Houſe ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Acts 11. 13, 14. Even ſo God hath ſent unto us Men and Women, the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Inhabitants of this Earth, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles, who have, and do tell us words, whereby we, and all ſuch as receive and obey the ſame words, ſhall be ſaved. Chriſt in an emphatical manner is called the <hi>Word,</hi> John 1. 1. and the word of God. For all the words which God made known through <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts and Apoſtles do all relate unto, and meet in him,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153618:13"/> as lines in their Centre. <hi>And all things were made by him,</hi> (the Word) <hi>and without him was not any thing made that was made.</hi> Here the Evangeliſt hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto <hi>John</hi> 1. 1. Pſal. 33. 6. So the certain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence is, That all Men and Women will be ſaved by him (the Word) that ſhall ever be ſaved. <hi>For there is no other way under Heaven given unto Men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we muſt be ſaved.</hi> And as <hi>Moſes</hi> of old time had, even ſo at this day Chriſt hath thoſe that Preach him every Sabbath day. Therefore <hi>ſee that ye refuſe not him that ſpeaketh; for if they eſcaped not who refuſed him that ſpake on Earth, much more ſhall not we eſcape, if we turn away from him that ſpeaketh from Heaven,</hi> Heb. 12. 25. For though Chriſt is long ſince aſcended on high, and ſits at the right Hand of God, yet he ſpeaks to us even now by his Word, and by his Miniſters; <hi>He that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my Words, hath one that jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth him; the Word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge him at the laſt day,</hi> John 12. 48. And if we will not hear that Word, nor yet his Miniſters, neither would we be perſwaded, if Chriſt ſhould come once again into the World after the ſame manner as he did: But his next coming is unto Judgment.</p>
            <p>I have often mentioned theſe and the like things, to the froward Inhabitants of this my Country and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, who are Non-Hearers, or Non-Readers of the Word, where-ever it is faithfully and truly Preached, or made known. I have warned them often, and I do hereby warn them again, and I could almoſt tell them weeping, (for my Soul hath Grief and Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at them for their ſtubbornneſs and refuſal herein) That ſince that his Word is every Sabbath day, or Week day, purely, truly, and faithfully Preached, or made known, God will require it of them, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it as Sin to them, ſeverally, for as often as they have neglected to come to hear it.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153618:14"/>
            <p>Hereby alſo may be ſeen and perceived, How much this Ordinance of Preaching the Word doth further, and is abſolutely neceſſary unto the Salvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and how that ſuch Men and Women, who would indeed have their Souls be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus, ought, and muſt attend continually upon the Miniſtry, and hearing thereof; for this ſame Preaching of the Word, which doth lead, direct, and help towards obtaining the reſt to come, doth alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, that others may learn, in whatſoever ſtate they are in, the mean while therewith to be content; <hi>to know how to be full, and how to be hungry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho it be here ſurmiſed, nevertheleſs, That thoſe people alſo are content who do very ſeldom or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hear the word preached, much leſs are they frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of it. What advantage then of my preaching, and what profit of your hearing the word? <hi>Much eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way,</hi> chiefly becauſe it is an Ordinance, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God; for thoſe who have the gifts of preaching to preach and profit therewithal. But <hi>the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the ſpirit is given to every man to profit withal,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 7. For what if ſome do deſpiſe and refuſe to attend upon this Ordinance, ſhall their deſpiſing or Refuſal make this Ordinance of God of none effect? or that the <hi>word which goeth out of his mouth, ſhall return vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> In no wiſe, God forbid; for ſo it is, ſome will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aved by the Miniſtry of the Word; others will be condemned by it. Some will be more edified and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, others (thro their refuſal, and turning away their Feet from the place where it is preached with a lively Voice, will be more hardened, and rendred yet worſe, and more inflexible to the Exhortation thereof.)</p>
            <p>But it will be ſo much the better for every man or woman the more he or ſhe ſhall glorify God, and the more good they ſhall do in their Generation, as alſo the more they ſhall abſtain from all appearance of Evil.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153618:14"/> Now the Word, and the preaching thereof, doth help and aſſiſt us in theſe two points, to <hi>eſchew Evil, and do Good</hi> Unleſs theſe two Ends of Life, eſchewing Evil, and doing Good, are anſwered and obſerved, ir would be better not to have been born, or not to have lived at all. Moſt people, when they hear or read ſuch a Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture as this following, do not attend thtoughly to the full meaning and ſignification thereof; <hi>For all this they ſinned ſtill, and believed not his wondrous works. Therefore their days did he conſume in Vanity, and their Years in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> Pſal. 78. 32, 33. The Life of ſinners and ungodly is ſpent in one of theſe two either Vanity or Trouble. Ay but many think that the former of theſe is no Curſe or Puniſhment; For, as it is written, <hi>O ye ſons of men, how long will ye love Vanity?</hi> Pſal. 4. 2. And it is ſeen and experienced that they take mirth and delight therein. But to thoſe who have Faith and Knowledge, nothing ſounds ſo bad as to have their Days conſumed in Vanity, and their Years in trouble. Becauſe that every thing in this life tends to future Account one way or another. And to this thing of conſuming their Days in Vanity, ſucceeds loſs for all Eternity. Even a loſs of that Reward and Bleſſedneſs God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and reſerved for his Creatures, if ſuch had been found worthy, and had been meet to have been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers thereof. <hi>Caſt the unprofitable Servant into utter darkneſs; there ſhall be Weeping and Gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi> Now Vanity and Unprofitableſs is near the ſame thing. And to them who thus conſumed their Years in trouble, will ſucceed endleſs Pains. Now to be miſerable here, and miſerable hereafter alſo is a ſad thing. For indeed, if they had conſumed their Years in trouble, in the way of Duty, in the Service of God, or in a Good thing, then indeed it might have been Reaſonably expected as to ſuch, the promiſe that they ſhould have <hi>Reſted from their Labours,</hi> and they were of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153618:15"/> the Number of thoſe, who through <hi>Manifold Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould enter into the Kingdom of God;</hi> And the return ſhould have been made upon them when they arrived there, <hi>Theſe are they that have came through Great Tribulation.</hi> But whereas contrarywiſe as it is in the Words of our Pſalmiſt, <hi>They ſinned ſtill;</hi> then the only conſequent which they will meet withal, is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation and Miſery hereafter. As for thoſe who ſin ſtill, or add ſin to ſin, againſt whom a <hi>Woe</hi> is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>They do Treaſure up to themſelves wrath againſt the Day of wrath:</hi> It is alike, yea, and the very ſame Folly and Madneſs, as for a Man himſelf to carry and heap on more fuel on that fire which ſhall burn and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him, but yet never conſume him. <hi>Many Sorrows ſhall be to the Wicked,</hi> Pſalm 32. 10 for whether his days are conſumed in Vanity (judge by the way, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no the conſuming ones time in Cards, Dice, Ale-houſes, Skettle-pins, Shufflboard, idle Talk, Play, Gaming, or ſuch like, is not conſuming ones days in Vanity, according to the intent of the Holy Ghoſt here) he ſhall ſuffer ſo much the more loſs through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Eternity; which ſome think to be the greateſt pain of Hell. Or whether their years are conſumed in Trouble; (as they all are in one or the other) to this ſucceeds Pain, and Puniſhment of Senſe, even more Miſery and Torment ſtill; which ſhall as much exceed his Trouble here, as to be thrown into a hot fiery Furnace is beyond a Flea-biting. Conſider of this ye that forget God, or who pretend to ſerve him a little in Form or Cuſtom, or outward Manner; but ye do not think much of him afterwards. Whoſe days are conſuming in Vanity, and whoſe Hearts are in trouble, or in doubt and fear about what your fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State and Condition will be. Bethink your ſelves throughly, and how can ye be content to go on in ſuch a kind of Life as that is? Know ye not, or do ye not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153618:15"/> believe it? However, ye will find it ſo that ye muſt give Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and ſuch an Account I tell ye before hand, of your days being conſumed in Vanity, ye will be forced to give up with Grief, and not with Joy, which will be unprofitable for ye. For here to allude again unto <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. The right conſequence is, and the word of Inſtruction to every one of ye is, ſeeing that we muſt all give Account, (for noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>g is ſo ſure and certain as that is) we ſhould ſo live in the mean while, that <hi>we may give up this ſame Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with Joy, and not with Grief, for that will be profitable for us.</hi> As was before ſaid, none will be, nor can be contented hereafter, to loſe Heaven, and fall into Hell: So now, in this ſhort mean while between, though the generality of the World is <hi>ſetled upon their Lee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> yet none ought, nor yet ſhould be contented with a vain, ſinful, or ungodly Life now, for this will bring them unto the other ſad thing.</p>
            <p>The ſenſual blinded World judge very much by Events; and becauſe (it may be) they have Health and Plenty, and things at will, and things continue as they were ſince the days of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they are apt to think that God is not angry or diſpleaſed with them. So it is in the Senſe and Mind of the Spirit, when a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or People commit a great deal of Sin, then God is angry with them; as again, when they pleaſe him, and he ſmells a ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from the Earth, then he hath Mercy on them. <hi>Then the Angel of the Lord anſwered and ſaid, O Lord of Hoſts, How long wilt thou not have Mercy on</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and on the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>againſt which thou haſt had Indignation theſe threeſcore and ten years.</hi> Zech. 1. 12. The words immediately foregoing are, <hi>All the Earth ſitteth ſtill, and is at reſt.</hi> So that the certain conſequence is, that God may have Indignation againſt the Inhabitants of the Earth at the very ſame time, when all the Earth ſitteth ſtill, and is at reſt; or at the very ſame time when the Inhabitants thereof are in Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity and Impunity, or without Puniſhment as yet. If you ſhould hereupon ask me, Whether the Lord God hath now Indignation theſe threeſcore years and ten? Or (during the time of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Generation.) againſt the Inhabitants of <hi>England,</hi> or againſt the Inhabitants of ſuch a particular Town or Neighbourhood? Or whether he hath Indignation againſt ſuch a Man or Woman at this very time, pointing them out by their ſeveral Names and reſpective Perſons. The anſwer hereunto is very critical, as we uſe to ſay, and I will be very careful herein. But as one inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his Word, I do believe, and tremble thereat, That the Lord God of Heaven hath at this very moment of my writing this, Indignation againſt the Inhabitants of <hi>England,</hi> and the Towns and Villages thereof; and in a word, againſt all thoſe ſeveral Men
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153618:16"/> and Women, taking them by their Names, or reſpective Perſons, who commit Sin, Iniquity, Tranſgreſſion, Hypocriſie, or any manner of Evil whatever.</p>
            <p>But ſome may be apt to ſay, How doth this appear that the Lord God hath Indignation againſt them? for have we not <hi>the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Weeks for the Harveſt?</hi> Bleſſed be God for that; and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient of Wheat and Barley for Bread, and Beer, and Cheeſe, and of all manner of Proviſion for the Life of man? Yea, was there not Peace in the midſt of our Nation, when the Nations Round about were weltring in blood? and even now they alſo, and we live in peace? Is it not likewiſe an Healthful time enough in all the Country Round about, ſo that there is no <hi>Plague, Peſtilence,</hi> or but ſcarce a <hi>malignant Fever?</hi> Bleſſed be God for that alſo. How then doth it appear that the Lord hath Indignation againſt <hi>England,</hi> and the Cities, Towns and Villages thereof? And then beſides, they go by multitudes to Church, or to ſuch and ſuch <hi>Congregations,</hi> to worſhip, attone, and pleaſe God. Thou muſt not make it worſe than it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. No, that I ought not to do in any wiſe. But yet when there is ſuch a Catalogue of Sins, Tranſgreſſions and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquities committed throughout this Nation, by the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, both High and Low, Rich and Poor, as is rehearſed up par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. when <hi>their Lies ſpeak Lies, and their Tongue muttereth Perverſneſs.</hi> People do not much Regard or heed whether they ſpeak Lies and Falſhood in their common Talk, and ordinary converſation. <hi>None calleth for Juſtice, nor any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for Truth; They trust in Vanity, and ſpeak Lies; they conceive Miſchief, and bring forth Iniquity,</hi> V. 4 And then the Prophet goes on to reckon them up; <hi>For our Tranſgreſſions are multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before thee, and our ſins testify againſt us.</hi> What is the Reſult and Conſequent of all we may Read, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>And the Lord ſaw it, and it diſpleaſed him.</hi> I will Repeat the ſame over again, that it may be more obſerved and taken notice of. <hi>And the Lord ſaw it, and it diſpleaſed him.</hi> So that certain it is, let ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Nation in general or the ſeveral people in particular, have never ſo much Peace and Plenty, Health or Proſperity, or all manner of outward Bleſſings <hi>(For God ſendeth Rain upon the juſt and the unjust, and is kind to the unthankful and Evil);</hi> Yet as long as they commit Sin, Iniquity. Tranſgreſſion, Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, Diſobedience, or any manner of Evil whatever, God hath at the very ſame time Indignation and Diſpleaſure againſt them: <hi>God is angry with the wicked every day,</hi> Pſal. 7. 11, Albeit the wicked do not believe, or rather they are not ſenſible of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt them.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:153618:16"/>
            <p>Now to apply all this. I ſhall begin from that Scripture, <hi>And as they did eat, Jeſus ſaid to the Twelve Diſciples, Verily I ſay unto you, that One of you ſhall betray me. And they were exceeding ſorrowful, and began every one of them to ſay, Lord, is it I?</hi> So this which we are now in, being a mixt Aſſembly of Saints and ſinners, Godly and Ungodly, it is odds but that the Lord God of Heaven and Earth hath indignation and diſpleaſure againſt ſome men and women herein; which is ſo nevertheleſs they have health and ſtrength; tho their ſtrength is firm; They are not in trouble as other men, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they plagued like other men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 4, 5. And ſo he hath had moſt or all the foregoing days of their Life. Whoſo hears or Reads this, had need to be exceeding ſorrowful, and begin every one of you to be upon the ſearch and Examination, <hi>Is it I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the Lord hath had Indignation theſe threeſcore years and ten,</hi> or ſo many years as I am old, and have lived? For <hi>the ſinner being an hundred years old ſhall be Accurſed.</hi> And who can abide, or ſtand before his Indignation? No man living, no more than ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doth before the devouring fire. The Counſel, Advice and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection which the Scripture gives herein, is to <hi>Agree with thine Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary quickly;</hi> and to forſake thoſe ſins which cauſe the Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord againſt any one.</p>
            <p>As on the one hand it is very terrible and bad to have the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, Diſpleaſure and Wrath of God, ſo on the other it is as good to have the Favour, Mercy and Loving Kindneſs of God. To be <hi>as Daniel</hi> was, <hi>Thou art greatly beloved, Dan.</hi> 9. 23. Or a man of Deſires. I had rather (though I am clothed with Rags, or in a Priſon) have this character from the Holy Ghoſt, than to be the greateſt Prince on Earth, ſitting on his Throne. And this may be Known the very ſame way as the other is; for as when people are given up to their own Hearts Luſts, and to follow their own counſel, when they ſin ſtill, and proceed <hi>from Evil to Evil;</hi> from bad to worſe; although they have never ſo much Health, Plenty and Proſperity; God hath nevertheleſs at the very ſame time Indignation and Diſpleaſure againſt them. So on the other hand, as we walk before him in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, in all Obedience and Duty, although the Saint or Servant, may be in a poor, adverſe and afflicted condition, as to outward things; yet God hath a Favour, Love and Mercy towards him at the very ſame time. This is a <hi>Myſtery</hi> to the people of the World, but yet it is a certain Truth. It comes to paſs through Ignorance, ſtupidity and ſtrong deluſions, which are annexed to the <hi>not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Love of the Truth.</hi> That moſt people, when they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Indignation of the Lord, they do not know as much, or they are not ſenſible of it, although they have little Glimpſes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153618:17"/> thereof by Remorſes of conſcience, and thoſe Fears and Doubts which ſometimes ariſe in their mind. So it is on the other ſide, the Saints and Servants of the Lord are always a Knowing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And hereby they Know and Perceive the Love and Favour of God towards them, by the Anſwer of <hi>a good conſcience</hi> from within them; when that ſpeaks <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> or <hi>Perfect Peace;</hi> ſuch as is true and ſound, in oppoſition and contradiſtinction to that Falſe and Rotten Peace of ignorant perſons and Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us now hear the concluſion of the whole matter.</hi> As we began, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we End. It was ſaid in the Entrance of this our Diſcourſe on <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 12. That I did therefore chuſe it as an help to avoid Evil (Eſpecially thoſe <hi>grievous Sins,</hi> of <hi>Diſtruſt, Murmuring,</hi> or ſuch like) which hath been accordingly ſhewed throughout the whole; that we may know both how to be abaſed, and how to abound, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, and in all things; we may be inſtructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer need; and in all this to ſin not, nor yet to charge God f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oliſhly, nor to ſuffer our hearts to fret againſt him. And on the other hand, in this Twofold Condition, or in that Even Middle ſtate between them both, <hi>to dwell in the Land, and do Good;</hi> ſerve God, and perform all our Duty towards him, our Neighbour or our ſelves; For he that would learn in whatſoever ſtate he is in, therewith to be content, or attain unto contentment (which, as one ſaith, is but another Phraſe for Happineſs) muſt do this. <hi>For he that will love Life, aad ſee Good Days,</hi> (is not all our Deſire and Endeavour after this, eſpecially the <hi>Life for evermore,</hi> and the good Days of Eternity) let <hi>him refrain his Tongue from Evil, and his Lips, that they ſpeak no Guile. Let him eſchew Evil. and do Good.</hi> (Here are the Two Ends of the Compaſs according to which we are to ſteer the whole courſe of our Life) <hi>Let him ſeek Peace, and enſue it; for the Eyes of the Lord are over the Righteous, and his Ears are open unto their Prayers; but the Face of the Lord is against them that do Evil,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 10, 11.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Written by <hi>Richard Stafford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Ralph Simpſon,</hi> at the <hi>Harp</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church yard. 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
